Today's דף *Daf* is ס"ט *Samech Tet*, 69. And we pick up
the אלא מונבז Munbaz? *Ela Munbaz*. It is three, six lines down.
And to remind us, there's a debate of אביי Abaye *Abaye*, רבא
Rava *Rava*, and שמואל *Shmuel* on one side and רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan, *Rabbi Yochanan* and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish. *Reish Lakish* on the
other about a תינוק שנשבה tinok shenishba, *Tinok Shenishba*, somebody that never
knew they were Jewish and they violate שבת Shabbos. *Shabbat*, that רבא
Rava *Rava* and שמואל *Shmuel* will say you still have to bring
one קרבן korban *Korban* for all of the violations, and רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish* say
you don't bring any קרבן korban *Korban* because, as we said, obviously
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish
Lakish* make sense, there's no fault, there's no guilt, but that רבא
Rava *Rava* and שמואל *Shmuel* presumably are working from a perspective that
a קרבן korban *Korban* is not just for personal guilt, it is
somehow to sort of cleanse the existence of the sin, and therefore
if you're the one that did it, you have to bring it
even if there is no fault. In the end actually, the רמב"ם
*Rambam* rules like רבא *Rava* and שמואל *Shmuel*. This debate is paralleled
by a debate of רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* and מונבז
Munbaz? *Munbaz* as well around this issue of the תינוק שנשבה *Tinok
Shenishba*. Now רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva, *Rabbi Akiva* said to מונבז Munbaz.
*Munbaz*, he said a reductio ad absurdum. He said מונבז Munbaz *Munbaz*'s
argument that you're exempt from a קרבן korban *Korban* is he said
it's like a מזיד mezid? *Meizid*, that the same way מזיד mezid
*Meizid* there's a knowledge and an awareness, by שוגג shogeg *Shogeg* as
well there had to have been an initial awareness. So רבי עקיבא
Rebbe Akiva, *Rabbi Akiva* did a reductio ad absurdum and he said
if that's true, make it totally like מזיד mezid *Meizid*, say you
should be aware even at the time of the committing of the
sin. And מונבז Munbaz *Munbaz* says sure, why not? So now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to say, well according to מונבז Munbaz
*Munbaz* what makes it a שוגג shogeg. *Shogeg* if you're even includes,
not only includes but even includes a case when you're aware at
the time of the sin? So that's the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s question.
ולמונבז שגגה במאי *V'leMunbaz shegaga b'mai*? According to מונבז Munbaz. *Munbaz*, where
is your error? If he is willing to include in a קרבן
חטאת korban chatas, *Korban Chatat* somebody who's aware at the time of
the sin, what's the error? What's the way in which it's not
just a מזיד meizid, *Meizid* and a willful sin? So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says כגון ששגג בקרבן *Kegon sheshagag b'korban*, that he knew
he was not allowed to do it, he knew that it was
violating a thing that was punishable by כרת kares. *Karet* or מיתה
mita, *Mitah* if there was witnesses and testimony, but he didn't realize
that it was a type of a sin that was obligated in
a קרבן korban *Korban*. And that is enough to say that he
now is enough in error that he can bring the קרבן korban.
*Korban*. It's a little bit ironic, you understand, because if the only
reason he's שוגג shogeg, *Shogeg* in the קרבן korban. *Korban* is because
the only reason there's a קרבן korban. *Korban* to make a mistake
with is because you're ruling that counts as a שוגג shogeg *Shogeg*
and it's obligated in a קרבן korban. *Korban*. Anyway, it seems a
little circular, but maybe it just means generally he wasn't aware that
it's a type of a sin that has a קרבן korban *Korban*
attached to it, and therefore there was enough of an error to
obligate him in the קרבן korban *Korban*, which is quite interesting that
that counts as enough.
Okay, so
that's מונבז Munbaz *Munbaz*. Now we move on to the רבנן *Rabbanan*,
which is the more mainstream position, and we want to figure out
normally when you say somebody is unaware so they bring a קרבן
korban *Korban*, what do they have to be unaware about? So let's
take a look. ורבנן שגגה במאי *Verabbanan shegaga
b'mai*? And according to the rabbis,
what are you unaware of in a normal case where you bring
a קרבן korban *Korban*? And normally you would say you're unaware that
this thing is prohibited. Okay, it's
and there's normally two scenarios of being unaware. Let either that, by
שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* there's actually three, but normally there's two scenarios of
being unaware. One is that, let's say it's about eating forbidden fat.
Either you don't know forbidden fat is forbidden, or this type of
forbidden fat is forbidden, but you don't know that the prohibition applies
to this thing. Or you know forbidden fat is forbidden, but you
make a mistake about the facts in front of you. You thought
this was a steak, you didn't realize this was חלב cheilev. *Chelev*.
Okay, so it's an error in the facts or an error in
the law. Those are your normal two types of שוגג shogeg *Shogeg*.
Now by שבת Shabbos, *Shabbat*, you could have essentially, you know, you
could either not know that this מלאכה melacha, *Melacha* is forbidden, or
you could have forgotten that today was שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*. Forget that
today was שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* is sort of like the error in
the facts. It's sort of like thinking this was a steak when
it's actually חלב cheilev. *Chelev*. You've got the facts wrong about what
day of the week it is. So those are generally the two
types of errors that you can make for a שוגג shogeg, *Shogeg*.
And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* knows that, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
wants to understand now that we're looking at the exact parameters, maybe
there's other scenarios of error that still counts as a שוגג shogeg.
*Shogeg* to bring a קרבן korban. *Korban*. So let's take a look.
For רבנן *Rabbanan*, and what was the Rabbi's state? שגגת קרבן korban.
לא lo, שמה שגגה *Shegagat korban lo shema shegaga*. That's not a
real error. Presumably that's also not the type of a thing you,
if you're aware about everything else, you're aware that it's prohibited, you're
aware that it's punishable by כרת kares, *Karet* or worse, then that's
enough of a reason you should not be doing this. And enough
that when you do it in violation of this, you're considered a
willful violator even if you're not aware of one aspect of a
small aspect of the consequence. Okay, so that's, so that's what the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says according to מונבז Munbaz, *Munbaz*, a very extreme
position, a very broad category of how much awareness you can have
and still bring a קרבן korban. *Korban*. So now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, okay, so that's מונבז *Munbaz*. Now we move on to
the רבנן *Rabbanan* which is the more mainstream position and we want
to figure out normally when you say somebody is unaware so they
bring a קרבן korban. *Korban*, what do they have to be unaware
about? So let's take a look. ורבנן שגגה במאי *Verabbanan shegaga b'mai*?
What's your שוגג shogeg. *Shogeg* in? So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. אומר
כיון ששגג בכרת אף על פי שהזיד בלאו *Rabbi Yochanan omer keivan
sheshagag b'Karet af al pi sheheizid b'lav*. This is a really... Amazing
idea. You can know you are violating, you know this is biblically
prohibited, but you don't know it's so severe. You think this is
just a normal לאו, lav. you didn't realize that this was punishable
by כרת. kares. Again, as we said yesterday, the only time you
bring a קרבן korban is for a prohibition that if you did
it willfully you would get כרת, kares okay, and maybe something even
worse in a בית דין. beis din. But even assuming there's no
בית דין beis din and there's no witnesses, it's a type of
a sin that's punishable by כרת. kares. Not every prohibition, only very
weighty ones. There's only 36 sins that you bring a קרבן korban
for that are punishable by כרת kares, or worse. So let's say
you know, yeah, I know I'm not supposed to eat חמץ chametz
on פסח, Pesach, but you know, I think it was like any
other לאו. lav I think it wasn't worse than חזיר, chazir, okay?
And most people assume חזיר chazir is worse. We have a regular,
we have a type of a taboo around חזיר. chazir.
Why does the average Jew think that way?
Yeah, I know.
So you know, I figured it wasn't worse than נבלה, neveilah, than
meat that wasn't שחט shechted properly. אכט וייס, Ach veis, it's חמץ
chametz on פסח. Pesach. So according to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan you
bring a קרבן korban. because you didn't realize how weighty it was.
You didn't realize it was punishable by כרת. kares, And presumably that's
not considered as severe of a willful violation. You're not willfully violating
it with awareness of how severe it is. You were willful and
intentional, but not with an awareness of how severe it is, and
therefore you can still bring a קרבן korban. to atone for it.
It still is enough deserving and able to be atoned for. Yes.
How's that different than מונבז? Than מזיד? meizid How's that different than
מונבז? It's the same thing.
Than מזיד meizid you mean? Than מונבז. No, מונבז says that even
if you're aware that it's punishable by כרת, kares, you just weren't
aware that there's a קרבן korban. associated with it.
Then you'd still bring a קרבן.
korban, Then you'd still bring a קרבן.
korban According to him too, right?
No, here, if you know it's כרת, kares? then you're חייב כרת.
chayav kares. If you know it's a לאו lav, and you don't
know it's כרת, kares then you bring a קרבן. korban Okay, now
an interesting question the גמרא Gemara. is asking is also one would
imagine is when do you get כרת? kares. Right? Because presumably you
get כרת kares, when there's no קרבן. korban The קרבן korban? is
for the case where you're not deserving of כרת. kares? So one
wonders if that's if רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying the same
thing, that knowing I'm willfully violating but not knowing it's deserving of
כרת, kares does it also mean that I don't get כרת? kares,
You know, I only get a קרבן korban or can there be
some grounds where you get both? You're deserving of כרת kares, but
you can also get a קרבן korban to get out of it?
The גמרא Gemara isn't addressing the circumstances that you get כרת, kares.
but it's addressing the circumstances that what you have done is not
so severe that you at least are able to bring a קרבן
korban for atonement. And according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, it's enough
that you weren't aware that it's punishable by כרת, kares, you weren't
aware how weighty it was, even though you knew it was prohibited.
Let me read ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish It's amazing. ריש לקיש אמר,
Reish Lakish Amar, and we rule like רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan And
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says what we would normally expect: no, only
if you're fully in error. You do what you think what you're
doing is permitted. You have to err both in the prohibition and
in the כרת. kares, But if what you know what you're doing
is a violation of a biblical prohibition, we cannot call you שוגג
shogeg? to bring a קרבן. korban Now even in ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish there's a possibility where you know you're not allowed to do
it, which is let's say by שבת. Shabbos. שבת Shabbos has a
מצות עשה mitzvas asei תשבות tishbos and a negative, right, לא תעשה
מלאכה. lo sa'aseh melachah. So let's say I know I'm not supposed
to work on שבת, Shabbos? but that's only because, you know, let's
say I was brought up in, you know, in a Christian household
like a תינוק שנשבה, where you talk about שבת Shabbos as a
day of rest, so I know, I think about it as a
positive command, I'm supposed to rest, I don't think about it as
a prohibition and as something that's punishable by כרת, kares but I
know I'm supposed to rest. So that's a case where you know
you're not supposed to do work, but you don't know you're violating
a prohibition, you only know that there's a positive command that you're
disregarding. So presumably for ריש לקיש Reish Lakish? that would still be
enough of a שוגג. shogeg Okay, so even in ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish he's not saying you have to think it's totally permitted. But
it's quite interesting and I would think quite encouraging, if you will,
that the rabbis are saying that people can be a certain degree
willful and still be able to get a קרבן. korban So according
to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, even if you know you're violating but
you don't know how severe it is, punishable by כרת, kares. and
according to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish you have to not know that
it's prohibited either, you know,
not know it's punishable by כרת kares. and not know it's prohibited.
But as I said, there's still a possibility that you could know
you're not supposed to do it. But as long as you don't
know that it's a לאו, lav a negative prohibition, you're still able
to bring a קרבן. korban. Yes.
So for רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan in order to be מזיד meizid.
you'd have to have perfect knowledge.
Yeah, knowledge that it's a לאו lav and כרת. kares I don't
know what you mean by perfect knowledge, that sounds like a trick
question, but you have to know it's a לאו lav, and כרת.
kares.
And you also have to have התראה hasra'ah and all that?
No, no, then you get punished by בית דין. beis din. This
is כרת kares, by God and without, and no קרבן. korban Yes.
We're talking only about negative commandments.
Right, the only time you bring a קרבן korban. is those two
criteria: it's a negative commandment and punishable by כרת. kares, A positive
thing with כרת, kares. like קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, no קרבן korban.
if you don't do it. And a negative thing without כרת, kares
no קרבן. korban The only way you bring a קרבן חטאת, korban
chatas and the other קרבנות korbanos are the same, but a קרבן
korban. חטאת is a negative prohibition plus כרת. kares Okay, so that's
their debate. So now the גמרא Gemara says... אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
מאי טעמא דרבי שמעון בן לקיש? mai ta'ama de'Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish?
What's the reason of ריש לקיש? Reish Lakish, Seems like pretty reasonable
reason, I mean just the logic of it, but we have a
פסוק. pasuk. אמר קרא, amar kra, the verse says,
אשר לא תעשינה ואשם. asher lo te'asena ve'ashem. You did something you
should not be doing and you have sinned. Okay, and so עד
שישגוג בלאו וכרת שבה. ad she'yishgog be'lav ve'kares she'bah. It's only a
case where you erred in the לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh. You erred
in the fact that you shouldn't be doing it. Okay, so your
error was you weren't even aware that you were prohibited from doing
it. רבי יוחנן, Rebbi Yochanan האי קרא דרבי שמעון בן לקיש מאי
עביד ליה? hai kra de'Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish mai avid lei? What
does he do with that verse of that you should not be
doing and you sinned, which seems like the error was in the
fact you shouldn't be doing it? How does he interpret it? מיבעי
ליה לכדתניא. mibaye lei lich'detanya. He needs it for what we taught
in a ברייתא. braisa. מעם הארץ. me'am ha'aretz. It says that one
of the people of the land sins in one of the sins
אשר לא תעשינה ואשם asher lo te'asena ve'ashem that should not be
done and sins, and then he brings a קרבן. korban? So what's
מעם הארץ? me'am ha'aretz? פרט למומר, prat le'mumar, to exclude somebody that
is an apostate, somebody that has basically rejected, said, I'm not, you
know, I'm just not buying into this whole system, I don't care
about all this stuff. So that type of a person is not
able to bring a קרבן. korban, Now you would say, oh, obviously
they can't bring a קרבן, korban. they're מזיד, meizid they're willfully sinning.
But the גמרא Gemara actually has a scenario, you know, let's say
a person basically rejected the whole thing, but today it just so
happened he was eating, he thought he was eating a steak and
he was eating חלב. chelev, So he wasn't intending to sin today,
right? So even though but in principle he's willing to sin, he's
rejected the whole category anyway. So you know what? Even when he
does תשובה teshuva he can't bring a קרבן korban for that act
because at that stage he was a מומר, mumar, he was in
a position where he completely had rejected the whole system. Yes,
he did תשובה teshuva later. Later in life he regrets everything that
he's done and now he wants to bring a קרבן korban, for
all those past sins. So even the sins you did in the
past when you were, which you did accidentally, since you were prepared
to do them intentionally and you were a מומר, mumar, you would
not bring a קרבן korban, for them. So it excludes the case
of a מומר. mumar. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar
says משום ר' שמעון, mishum Rebbe Shimon, now that we learn out
from מעם הארץ. me'am ha'aretz. But now you have a similar דרשה
drasha but it's from the פסוק pasuk from later in the פסוק,
pasuk, from this פסוק pasuk that ריש לקיש Reish Lakish focused
on, אשר לא תעשינה ואשם, asher lo te'asena ve'ashem, that you should
not be doing it and you sinned. And this tells us השב
מידיעתו מביא קרבן על שגגתו, hashav mi'yediato mevi korban al shigagaso, that
what type of a person brings a קרבן? korban It's sort of
getting at the same point, but rather than by labeling you as
a מומר, mumar, apostate, and categorically excluding you, we're focusing on the
individual act. And then the individual act we say, you bring a
קרבן korban. when it's a type of thing you would not have
done had you been aware.
אשר לא תעשינה ואשם. asher lo te'asena ve'ashem. You were not aware
and therefore you sinned. השב מידיעתו, hashav mi'yediato, somebody who had they
been aware, מידיעתו, mi'yediato, would have done תשובה, teshuva, would have not
done this action, had they been informed and aware you couldn't do
it, would not have done it. That's the type of person of
מביא קרבן על שגגתו, mevi korban al shigagaso, brings the קרבן korban,
when you make an error. לא שב מידיעתו, lo shav mi'yediato, if
even had you been informed you would have gone ahead and done
it, אינו מביא קרבן על שגגתו, eino mevi korban al shigagaso, you
would not bring a קרבן korban, on your error. So exactly the
same scenario: here's a guy that said to the heck with it,
I'm not keeping anything, and today he happens to eat something he
thinks is a steak and it turns out to be חלב. chelev,
So even if later he does תשובה, teshuva, he would not bring
a קרבן korban. for that. According to one, because as a person
you're a מומר, mumar, and מומרים mumarim are excluded from קרבנות. korbanos.
And according to the second דרשה, drasha, it's we're not categorizing you
as a person, but what we're saying is that you can't call
this an error if even had you been aware, you would have
done it anyway. The only time you bring a קרבן korban is
in a case where were you made aware of the issues you
would have not done it. Since you would have gone ahead and
done it regardless, you do not bring a קרבן. korban It gets
to the same point. There's a גמרא Gemara that tries to figure
out a case that would be a debate between whether it's about
defining the person as a מומר mumar and categorically excluding him, or
focusing on the particular act. But anyway, it is two ways to
get to a very similar conclusion, and that's what you do with
this פסוק. pasuk. Now תוספות Tosafos asks the obvious question, which is,
okay, so presumably we're agreeing that the only case you bring a
קרבן korban is somebody who, had they known, wouldn't sin. So what
we have to be asserting according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. is
that even though you know you're violating, were you aware how weighty
it was, that would have made the difference, right? Yeah, I know
I'm eating חמץ, chametz, but big deal, it's not worse than נבילה,
neveila, which I eat every day anyway, or whatever the case might
be. Like the joke, I don't eat חמץ chametz on יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, anyway,
people, whatever.
Anyway, okay, forget that. Anyway, so, so according to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan you have to say that if he says that not knowing
כרת kares. makes you enough of a שוגג, shogeg. he's saying two
things. He's saying number one, that's enough so that we're not going
to call you a, you know, we're going to call you enough
in error that you're entitled to a קרבן. korban We're not going
to call you a fully willful sinner that you get כרת kares
and that you're not deserving. And you're not entitled to a קרבן.
korban Number one. But number two is we have to say that
you fit into this box that is we assume you would have
stopped doing it had you been aware how weighty it was because
the case that you bring a קרבן korban, is also has to
be a case where had you known all the facts and had
you known the law you would not have done it. And we
have to assume that even though you knew you were willfully you
were transgressing a לאו, lav, you would have stopped doing it had
you known that it was deserving of כרת. kares. You had a
question, Charlie? No? Okay. Yes, Dov?
So I was just thinking about the idea we discussed the other
day about
a rupture that's repaired by a קרבן. korban. So in all these
kind of middle cases where it's not exactly מזיד meizid but it's
not a שוגג shogeg. anymore, how does how does that get accounted
for or does anyone...
What do you mean? You mean that you don't bring a קרבן?
korban. Right. Well I mean the no it's a bigger question. The
cases that are מזיד that there's no קרבן, korban how do those
get repaired for? Right? So you know that's a big question. So
to say... What's the person supposed to...
Right, right, so that's a but right, so is the punishment either
by God or by בית דין beis din while that sort of
you know is what he is deserving for his transgression if this
idea that there's a sin out there that needs to be cleansed,
you know, how do you understand that? So to some degree I
think the קרבנות korbanos of יום כיפור Yom Kippur according to חז"ל,
Chazal, you know part of what that does is it's מכפר mechaper
even on even on מזיד. It's you know whatever, there's some debates
around that. But but what's your question? Is is it because how
is it different than the מזיד case?
It's not really. But with the מזיד case I assume that the
person's punishment
as administered replaces that fault.
So your question is that according to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish you
have a case you have a case that falls between the cracks,
that you don't get כרת kares and you don't get a קרבן.
korban So I don't that's what I was raising before. The גמרא
Gemara doesn't discuss the scope of כרת. kares,
Intuitively you would say that כרת kares, picks up where קרבן korban,
ends. So according to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish if you're a willful
violator and you're not aware of כרת, kares that you don't bring
a קרבן, korban, then presumably you get כרת, kares? although I understand
why you would get כרת kares even if you weren't aware that
you were deserving it. Is that really fair? But maybe, you know?
Okay, but that's a good question. Does ריש לקיש Reish Lakish have
a gap where you're not, you know, bad enough to bring a
קרבן, korban. you're too willful to bring a קרבן korban but not
willful enough or not aware enough that you're deserving of כרת? kares
And I don't know, the גמרא Gemara does not explore that question.
Yes, Michael?
So I was going to say because according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan. then if you thought that it was instead of כרת kares,
it was מיתה בידי שמים misa bidei shamayim that wouldn't be good
enough, right? Because
תוספות Tosafos says you know you have to be שוגג shogeg? enough
that you would have stopped otherwise, right? But if you're confusing כרת
kares, מיתה בידי שמים misa bidei shamayim then that's not enough to
to get you onto a קרבן. Korban.
I don't know. What what are you saying? Would you be שב
מידיעתו shav mi-yedi'aso had I known that it was I don't know
if you know that it's very severe but not exactly as severe...
Yeah, and also from מונבז when we say that that your mistake
was with the קרבן, Korban. like would it even be like, 'Oh,
I thought I had to bring a שעיר se'ir as opposed to
a כשבה,' kesavah, whatever.
Yeah, I don't know. But I do think it is worth mentioning
that it's very difficult to understand for מונבז that even if you
make a mistake in the קרבן, Korban you're entitled to bring a
קרבן. Korban, How does that fit into the category of שב מידיעתו?
shav mi-yedi'aso? What? I know I'm deserving of כרת, karais. I know
it's biblically prohibited, but had you told me there's also a קרבן
korban. with it, then I wouldn't have done it. I mean, that's
pretty bizarre. So I think that that's a real question. Exactly those
tiny nuances, I don't know. I mean, that's not explicit in the
גמרא. Gemara, Yes?
How about someone who is who believes in some of the commandments
and not others, such as a conservative rabbi who says you can
drive to שול shul on שבת Shabbos, but you shouldn't eat חמץ
chametz and he accidentally eats חמץ? chametz?
Okay, so I'm not going to talk about particular denominations or whatnot.
But I will say, and also there's a difference between having a
different belief, which is אומר מותר, omer mutar, which is sort of
like this, thinking it was never prohibited, as opposed to willful rejection,
which is the מומר mumar case. But the גמרא Gemara actually deals
with a מומר mumar for one category and not for another category
and it exactly finds in that the difference between whether you approach
it categorically as a מומר mumar and then okay, once you're labeled
a מומר mumar you're completely excluded, or whether it's about this act
you would have otherwise not done, and therefore מומר mumar for one
might not apply to another. So the גמרא Gemara actually does deal
with that elsewhere. Yes?
In terms of the...
Right, so that's a good question. So a lot of the קרבנות
korbanos is sort of is a what's called an honor system. Okay,
and there is a גמרא Gemara that deals with the fact about
if somebody says you're obligated in a קרבן korban, and you deny
it, whether you have to listen to what the witnesses say or
whether it's sort of like you're trusted because in the end of
the day it's your כפרה. kaparah. So that is a good question.
So let's continue. Now what the גמרא gemara will do is focus
on this debate of ריש לקיש Reish Lakish and רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan around this issue about whether you have to whether you can
bring a קרבן korban even if you know it's prohibited as long
as you don't know it's punishable by כרת, karais, or whether you
have to be fully in error, which is fully think it's permitted,
which
is... Okay so we are here sort of leaving the category of
תינוק שנשבה *tinok shenishba* and now transitioning into this discussion about whether
you have to be fully in error or partially in error to
bring a קרבן korban. *korban* and I just do want to say
what I said yesterday is that תינוק שנשבה *tinok shenishba* beyond this
very narrow question of do you bring a קרבן korban, *korban* or
not you know it becomes an extremely important model of a symbol
of like an idea concept like just the idea of תינוק שנשבה
*tinok shenishba* as somebody that because of their background cannot be held
accountable for not observing the law. And for the רמב"ם *Rambam* it
was a way of having a more sort of forgiving approach towards
the קראים *Karaites* that even though they knew they were Jewish but
they had a different perception of what their obligations were. And the
בית יוסף *Beit Yosef*, the author of the שולחן ערוך *Shulchan Aruch*
followed in that. And then it had a profound implication nowadays post
the enlightenment post the השכלה *Haskalah* where you know not where you
know 90
percent of the Jews or whatever the number is you know don't
believe they're obligated in הלכה *Halacha*. And they are brought up that
way you know and so how much accountable can you be for
not believing and being brought up in a you know in a
culture and by you know in an you know in a way
in which you're taught that this is not your obligation. The interesting
thing comes then those that want to sort of you know extend
that also sense of inclusiveness even even if somebody is brought up
פרום *frum* and then they wind up leaving it based on the
general you know you know based on the fact that it's an
open society and so on and how hard it is to remain
in a you know in a sort of in a committed belief.
But this idea of תינוק שנשבה *tinok shenishba* becomes a very powerful
concept you know for this approach of inclusiveness and you know sort
of going the גמרא gemara *Gemara* sees that anybody who's a willful
שבת Shabbos, *Shabbas* violator מחלל שבת Shabbos. בפרהסיא *mechallel Shabbas b'farhesya* is
excluded. The idea of תינוק שנשבה *tinok shenishba* is a very powerful
concept for inclusion. It has within it a negative side that it's
a little patronizing it's really saying that you can't be held accountable
for your beliefs and therefore we'll include you. And I've written an
article about other approaches to this but it's important to be aware
of how powerful תינוק שנשבה *tinok shenishba* is as a concept. Okay
now we continue at the two dots where we're going to continue
to discuss this new debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. *Rabbi Yochanan*
and ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*. תנן *Tnan*. אבות מלאכות melachos *Avot melachot*
are ארבעים חסר אחת *arbaim chaser achat*. We're going to say a
משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* which is 40 that there's 39 categories of מלאכה
melacha. *melachah*. And I mentioned this the other day. דאוינן בהן *De'avinan
ban* we asked מניינא למה לי *minyana lama li*. Why do you
have to tell us 39? I can count. It seems to be
telling us that there's some significance about these as independent categories and
as being 39. ואמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. *Ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan* so
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* says שאם עשאן כולם בהעלם אחד
*she'im asan kulam be'helam echad* חייב chayav. על כל אחת ואחת *chayav
al kol achat ve'achat* to tell you that you can bring on
any one שבת Shabbos. *Shabbas* up to 39 חטאות *chatas's* because if
you forgot that every single one of them was forbidden then you
would go ahead and you would have done 39 different categories of
מלאכה melacha, *melachah* and you bring 39 חטאות *chatas's* because what we
learned in the first משנה *Mishnah* what we learned yesterday is that
it's not like שבת Shabbos *Shabbas* is one עבירה *aveirah* and it's
like eating a piece of חמץ chametz, *chametz* ten different pieces of
חמץ *chametz* where if you forgot it was
פסח *Pesach* that's one קרבן korban. *korban* or you forgot you didn't
know these things were חמץ *chametz* it's one קרבן korban *korban* because
it's the same עבירה *aveirah* multiple times. By שבת Shabbos *Shabbas* every
different מלאכה melacha? *melachah* category is seen as a different עבירה *aveirah*.
So since there are 39 מלאכה melacha, *melachah* categories if you forget
each one of them then you can bring up to 39 חטאות
*chatas's* for one on one שבת Shabbos *Shabbas*. And that's why it
told you the number.
What? How does it answer the question why do you need the
numbers though if it just lists for you the 39?
Yeah but to tell you that right but to tell to tell
you that this is not just a convenient organizational principle which we
might have thought right? It's to tell you that right that there
really is a significance of the number of categories the number determines
the number of קרבנות korbanos. *korbanot* you will bring. Okay because you
could have just thought who cares whether I call this I could
have come to the same prohibited scope of activities by making 10
categories rather than 39 what difference does it make? Why do I
need 39? It says no the number makes a difference.
Why is it say 40 minus 1? A-ha okay that's an interesting
question that's just you know probably A) it's a way of counting
you know because we like round numbers. The תורה Torah *Torah* says
ארבעים יכנו *arbaim yakenu* and the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says it doesn't
mean forty lashes it means 39. So that idea of 40 minus
1 like is a concept you know particularly from that lashes. But
we'll talk about that more when we get to the משנה *Mishnah*.
So let's take a look. דהא *De-ha* so the גמרא gemara *Gemara*
says חייב על כל אחת ואחת *chayav al kol achat ve'achat*. היכי
משכחת לה mashkachas lo, *Hechi mashkachat lah*? So how what's the case
where you get 39
a you know separate קרבן korban *korban* for every act for every
מלאכה melacha *melachah* category? בזדון שבת Shabbos, ושגגת מלאכות melachos *Bezedon Shabbas
vishigagat melachot*. You knew it was שבת Shabbos *Shabbas* you just did
not know that these were prohibited activities right? Because if you didn't
know it was שבת Shabbos, *Shabbas* then it would only be one
קרבן korban? *korban* like we said yesterday. So now the גמרא gemara
*Gemara* has an interesting question. בשלמא *Bishlama* how do you know it's
שבת Shabbos *Shabbas*? If you think all 39 categories are permissible how
do you know it's שבת Shabbos *Shabbas*? What makes it שבת Shabbos
*Shabbas*? So the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says בשלמא לרבי יוחנן *bishlama le-Rabbi
Yochanan* according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* I understand דאמר
כיון דשגיג בכרת אף על פי שמזיד בלאו *de'amar kivan deshageig bekareit
af al pi shemezid belav* that you could bring a קרבן korban,
*korban* even if you know it's prohibited as long as you don't
know it's punishable by כרת karais, *kareit*. case, so I can understand
how you don't know about these things enough to bring a קרבן,
korban. but you still know it's שבת. Shabbos משכחת לה, because you
can find the case כגון דידע לה לשבת בלאו. kegon d'yada lah
leshabbos belav. You know all these categories are prohibited with a negative
prohibition of doing מלאכה, melacha but you just don't know they're punishable
by כרת. karet. But because you don't know how weighty they are,
you would bring a קרבן korban, for every violation and you'd bring
39 קרבנות. korbanos? That's according to רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan אלא ריש
לקיש דאמר עד שישגוג בלאו ובכרת, Ella Reish Lakish d'amar ad sheyishgog
belav uvekarais,
according to ריש לקיש that says you have to think not only
that there's no כרת, karet, you only bring a קרבן korban when
you think it's not even prohibited. So how can you bring 39
קרבנות? korbanos How do you know it's שבת Shabbos, if you think
all these things are really permissible? How do you know it's שבת?
Shabbos So the גמרא gemara says, וידע ליה לשבת במאי? v'yada lei
leshabbos bemai?
In what way do you know it's שבת Shabbat, if you think
all these activities are permissible? So the גמרא Gemara says, וידע ליה
בתחומין ואליבא דרבי
עקיבא. v'yada lei b'tchumin v'aliba d'Rebbe Akiva. There's one final thing left
which is according to רבי עקיבא in a גמרא, Gemara, in another
גמרא Gemara in ביצה, Beitzah, whatever, in חגיגה Chagigah I think, where's
רבי
עקיבא,
anyway, that רש"י Rashi says, סוטה, Sotah, excuse me. He says that
תחומין tchumin are דאורייתא. d'oraisa. לא תצא איש ממקומו Lo seitzei ish
mimkomo from which don't go out of your place means don't go
out of the
environs of the city that he says that that's not an אסמכתא,
asmachta, that's really biblical, that you cannot go beyond the city limits.
So that's a לאו, lav, it's not כרת, karet. it's not a
מלאכה. melacha So I know it's שבת, Shabbos I know I'm not
supposed to go out of the city, but I think all this
activity is מותר. muttar. So at least I do know it's שבת,
Shabbos I know there's implications in this one area even though I
think all these מלאכות melakhot. are permissible. Now תוספות Tosafos asks a
couple of good questions. He says there's other ways you could know
that it's שבת. Shabbos If you take a look at תוספות, Tosafos,
he says, וידע ליה בתחומין, v'yada lei b'tchumin,
he says two lines into that תוספות, Tosafos, תימה לרי דאמאי לא
קאמר דידע ליה לשבת בעשה דכתיב וביום השבת תשבות וכתיב נמי ושמרתם
את השבת, Teima l'Ri d'amai lo ka'amar d'yada lei leshabbos be'asei, d'ksiv
uvyom hashabbos tishbos, uksiv nami ushmartem es hashabbos, וידע ליה בתחומין, v'yada
lei b'tchumin,
I just skipped the line into it. Okay, so anyway he says
you could know that you're not supposed to do these מלאכות but
as I told you before only maybe you think it's only a
מצות עשה, mitzvas asei, I'm supposed to rest. You don't know that
it's a negative, so maybe that's the case so you could still
know it's שבת. Shabbos, And as long as you don't know it's
prohibited with a negative prohibition, that should be enough to tell me
that I'm allowed to bring a קרבן, I'm enough in error because
I didn't know it was prohibited with a negative prohibition. תוספות Tosafos
doesn't know why it didn't give that answer. On the bottom you
have a תוספות ישנים Tosafos Yeshanim that asks even another question. He
says
a couple of things which I'll skip, but he says the question
I first asked is, why can't you say that you know that
certain things are, let's say I know that it's forbidden to plant,
but I didn't know that it's forbidden to water my plants. Okay,
so I could transgress all 39 categories knowing that they're prohibited but
not knowing the particular thing I did fell into that
category. So that's a way I could know it's שבת Shabbos. and
not know what I was doing was prohibited even though I know
the larger category is still prohibited. So that I think is a
very good question which he doesn't really have
a satisfactory answer to. And then he has other possibilities. Okay, now
there's also the question about is it enough to know it's שבת
Shabbos. if you just know שבת Shabbos. in the positive sense. תוספות
Tosafos says the positive of the עשה asei of תשבות, tishbos, but
that תשבות tishbos means don't do מלאכה, but it's saying it in
a positive way. Let's say you say I know it's שבת, Shabbos.
I know there's an idea of כבוד ועונג, kavod v'oneg, or I
know there's a מצוה mitzvah of קידוש. kiddush. Is that enough to
say that I knew it was
שבת Shabbos and I just didn't know the מלאכה? Because if I
didn't even know that it was שבת, Shabbos, then it's only one
קרבן. So is there an element that I have to know, it
sounds like from the גמרא Gemara that knowing it's שבת Shabbos. means
at least knowing that something is not allowed to be done, not
that I have to do something. And therefore it says תחומין tchumin
according to רבי עקיבא, but I think the other question that תוספות
Tosafos says, how about the מצות עשה mitzvas asei which also
implies you don't do certain things, or what I said you know
the general category but you don't know that this falls into that
category, there seems to have been other answers. Okay, but this is
a way you can bring all 39 even according to ריש לקיש
that says that you have to actually think that it's not even
prohibited by a negative prohibition. So now the גמרא Gemara continues. מאן
תנא להא דתנו רבנן? Man tanna leha d'tanno rabbanan? Who taught that
which our rabbis taught?
שוגג בזה ובזה זהו שוגג גמור בשבת. Shogeg bezeh uvezeh zehu shogeg
gamur b'shabbos. If you didn't know it was שבת Shabbos, and didn't
know that it was a מלאכה, that's a full שוגג, shogeg unquestionably
a שוגג. shogeg. מזיד בזה ובזה זהו מזיד על התורה. Meizid bezeh
uvezeh zehu meizid al hatorah. If you knew that it was שבת
Shabbos and you knew that this was
prohibited, that's a willful violator. שוגג בשבת ומזיד במלאכה. Shogeg b'shabbos umeizid
bimelacha. If you didn't know it's שבת Shabbos, but you knew these
things are prohibited on שבת, Shabbos you just thought it was Wednesday.
או ששוגג במלאכות ומזיד בשבת, O sheshogeg bimelachos umeizid b'shabbos, or you
knew it was שבת Shabbos but you thought that this act was
not prohibited, you didn't know you couldn't water your plants. Oh, those
are the two cases in the משנה, different amount of קרבנות korbanot
you bring, but those are the two cases in the. In the
משנה *Mishnah*, so so far it's just everybody agrees, but now we
add the kicker. או שאמר *o she'omar*, or you say, יודע אני
שמלאכה זו אסורה *yodea ani shemlocha zu asura*, I know you're not
allowed to water your plants on שבת Shabbos. *shabbos*. אבל איני יודע
שחייבין עליה קרבן *aval eini yodea shechayavin aleha korban* or not. חייב
*chayav*. So that is still enough to bring to bring a קרבן
*korban*. You're enough of in error because you didn't know it included
a קרבן *korban*. So who's that going like? That even an error
of a קרבן *korban* is enough to say that you're not fully
willful and you can bring a קרבן *korban*? כמאן *keman*, who is
this like? כמנבז *k'munbaz*, like מנבז *Munbaz* that we said before, even
just in error of a קרבן *korban*. אמר אביי amar Abaye, *amar
Abaye*, אביי Abaye *Abaye* says, הכל מודים hakol modim. בשבועת ביטוי *hakol
modim b'shvuat bituy* שאין חייבין עליה קרבן עד שישגוג בלאו שבה ad
sheyishgog b'lav shebah. *she'ein chayavin aleha korban ad sheyishgog b'lav shebah*. So
the תורה *Torah* says that there is a type of a case
where you bring a קרבן *korban* even when it's not punishable by
כרת karet, *karet*. It's a special קרבן *korban*, a קרבן עולה ויורד
*korban oleh v'yored*, a קרבן *korban* you bring for making, amongst other
things, for making a false שבועה shvua. *shvuah*. You make a שבועה
shvua *shvuah* and you say I will do something or I won't
do something and then you violate it. Or you make a שבועה
shvua. *shvuah* about the past, I didn't do something, I did do
something, and you're lying. Those types of cases where you make a
false שבועה shvua *shvuah* and you sin in error, okay, you would
actually you bring a קרבן *korban* even though it's not punishable by
כרת karet *karet*. So comes along אביי Abaye *Abaye*, so that's just
a category of something where you bring a קרבן *korban* even without
כרת karet *karet*. Comes along אביי *Abaye* says, everybody agrees in that
category, בשבועת ביטוי *bishvuat bituy*, שאין חייבין עליה קרבן עד שישגוג בלאו
שבה *she'ein chayavin aleha korban ad sheyishgog b'lav shebah*, that you're not
חייב *chayav* a קרבן *korban* until you make an error in the
לאו *lav*. It's not enough to make an error in the כרת
karet. *karet*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says what do you mean?
There is no כרת karet *karet*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
הכל מודים *hakol modim*, what do you mean everybody agrees? מאן *man*,
who is that? רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*. Even רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* who normally says it's enough to make an
error in the כרת karet, *karet*, here he says you have to
make an error in the לאו *lav*. פשיטא pshita? *peshita*, of course
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* would agree. כי קאמר רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan. היכא דאיכא כרת karet *ki ka'amar Rabbi Yochanan heicha d'ika
karet*. When רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* says it's enough to
be wrong about the כרת karet. *karet* is when there's a כרת
karet *karet* to be wrong about, when it's like a normal thing
like שבת Shabbos. *shabbos*. אבל הכא דליכא כרת karet, *aval hacha d'leika
karet*, by this case of a קרבן *korban* for a false שבועה
shvua *shvuah*, so there's no כרת karet, *karet* anyway. So the only
thing you can be wrong about is about the fact that it's
prohibited. What else could you be in error about? So לא *lo*,
of course he would not say that even if you're just in
error of כרת karet *karet*, right? Get it? There's only one thing
here, there's no כרת karet. *karet*, there's a prohibition. So what error
did you make? The only error you could make is that it
was prohibited. So of course רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* would agree that's
the error that you have to make. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says no. סלקא דעתך אמינא *salca daitach amina*, no, you have to
tell this to me. I might have thought according to רבי יוחנן
*Rabbi Yochanan*, הואיל וחיוב קרבן חידוש chiddush. הוא *ho'il v'chiyuv korban chiddush
hu*. Here, that you bring a קרבן *korban* for a false שבועה
*shvuah*, it's a חידוש *chiddush*. דבכל התורה כולה לא אשכחן לאו דאתי
עליה קרבן *d'bechol haTorah kullah lo ashkechan lav d'ati aleh korban*. In
all other places in the תורה *Torah*, we never find a simple
prohibition that you bring a קרבן *korban*, you normally only it's when
it's כרת karet *karet*. והכא מייתי *v'hacha meiti*, and here you bring
it even though there's even though it's a simple לאו *lav*. I
might have thought כי שגג בקרבן נמי ליחייב *ki shagag b'korban nami
l'ichayev*. Maybe here רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* switches into מנבז *Munbaz*. Right,
ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* is the one that says for to bring
a קרבן *korban* I need you to be fully in error to
not even know it's prohibited. רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* allows a partial
error, even if you just don't know that it's punishable by כרת
Kares *karet*. Now, you switch to a case like שבועת ביטוי *shvuat
bituy* where there's only a negative prohibition. So maybe רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan* says, well look, the fact that תורה *Torah* demands a קרבן
*korban* here normally it shouldn't because there's no כרת Kares. *karet* means
that we're being very demanding, we're going out of our way to
make sure you bring a קרבן *korban* in this case. If that's
true, I'll switch what I normally say, a partial error for כרת
Kares *karet*, and I'll replace it for a partial error for קרבן
*korban*. So maybe here I'll agree to מנבז *Munbaz*. And even if
you just made a mistake regarding the קרבן *korban*, that's enough to
bring a קרבן *korban*. מהו דתימא mahu d'teima? *mahu d'teima* for רבי
יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* who normally is okay with a partial mistake and
normally though not the mistake of קרבן *korban*, that's too trivial, but
a mistake of כרת Kares *karet*, but says maybe here by the
שבועה *shvuah* I would have thought that he would say even a
mistake of a קרבן *korban* because the תורה *Torah* is so demanding
that you bring the קרבן *korban* in this case. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says קמ"ל *ka mashma lan* that he's not going to
say that. That here basically רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* is consistent and
he other than מנבז *Munbaz* nobody says a mistake about a קרבן
*korban* is enough. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continue even
in this case here about the שבועה *shvuah*. So let's take a
look what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does with this. מיתיבי *meitivei*, I
ask you on this. איזו היא שגגת שבועת ביטוי לשעבר *eizo hi
shegagat shvuat bituy l'shavar*? What's a case of a mistake in the
past about a false שבועה *shvuah* that you would bring a קרבן
*korban*? Meaning think about the scenario. Somebody says and swears, I swear
I never, you know, whatever, I never ate that apple that you're
accusing me of eating. Now, if I'm willfully lying, I'm מזיד *mezid*,
I don't bring a קרבן *korban*. So I have to be a
שוגג shogeg *shogeg*. What's the example you would think that I'm a
שוגג shogeg *shogeg* when I swear that I didn't eat the apple?
The most obvious example? What would you
think? I forgot, right? I swear I didn't do it but I
thought I didn't do it but I really did but I totally
forgot. You would say that that's a שוגג shogeg? *shogeg*. So the
גמרא gemara *Gemara* says that's even better than a שוגג shogeg. *shogeg*.
There, when you are not aware of the of the of the
facts when you're making a שבועה *shvuah* on, you're actually in error
and you think you're swearing truthfully, then you're considered like an אונס
essentially for purposes of a שבועה. Other types of case when you
make a mistake by the facts, like I thought this was a
steak, it was חלב, I'm a שוגג. shogeg But here, the nature
of the oath, you know, if at the time I believe it's
a true שבועה and I'm just in error in my head, I
got the facts mixed up, the גמרא even in שבועות shvuot says
that that's actually not a false שבועה. Okay, so I haven't even
violated it at all. So what's the שוגג? Shogag. The only possible
שוגג shogeg is that I know I ate the apple, I know
I'm swearing falsely, but
I think it's okay to swear falsely. I never read the Ten
Commandments. Okay, so let's take a look. Okay, so
אלו שגגות שבועת ביטוי לשעבר? eilu shegagot shvuat bitui lashavar? יודע אני
ששבועה הוא אסורה. yodea ani sheshvua hu asura. So here it gives
a case where not like you actually think you're allowed to swear
falsely, that would be an easy case. We're going to give him
a little more challenging
case. I know I'm swearing falsely, I know I'm not allowed to
do it, אבל איני יודע אם חייב בקרבן או לא? aval eini
yodea im chayav b'korban o lo? חייב. So I don't know if
I have to bring a קרבן. So says, 'Ah, you see? Not
knowing that you have to bring a קרבן is enough of a
שוגג.' shogeg So the גמרא says, 'No, הא מני מונבז היא.' ha
mani munbaz hee. That's מונבז. Okay, it doesn't prove that. Only מונבז
is the one that says that a קרבן mistake is enough of
a שוגג. shogeg Otherwise you need to really think that it's either
permitted or for רבי יוחנן that you have to think at least
it's not weighty and deserving of כרת. Kares, In the case of
שבועה where there is no כרת, Kares, unless you're מונבז, you have
to really think it's permitted. Okay, now the גמרא continues. We'll skip
the parenthesis. ואמר אביי. v'amar Abaye. So that's number one about the
שבועה case. There there's no קרבן, you have to think it's permitted
according to רבי יוחנן. אמר amar, אביי, אביי said, הכל מודים בתרומה,
hakol modim b'terumah, everyone agrees when it comes to תרומה, terumah, שאין
חייב עליה חומש עד שישגוג בלאו שבה. she'ein chayav aleha chomesh ad
sheyishgog b'lav shebah. So this is not a קרבן, but here the
תורה says like this: If you eat תרומה terumah accidentally, thinking it's
non-תרומה, terumah, and you're not a כהן, kohen, you have to, and
you did it accidentally, you give it back and you add a
חומש. chomesh. And the extra חומש chomesh that you add also becomes
תרומה. terumah. So here also we have to ask, what are the
parameters of שוגג? shogeg What does it mean accidentally? So again, the
easiest שוגג shogeg? is always you're making a mistake about the facts.
You didn't know it was שבת, Shabbos, you didn't know that this
was חלב, you didn't know it was חמץ, you didn't know that
this was תרומה. terumah. That's the easy שוגג. shogeg You made an
error about the facts. We're asking the type of a שוגג that
is an error about the law. Okay, and we've been saying according
to, there's a debate of רבי יוחנן and ריש לקיש about whether
you have to think it's not prohibited or just not know how
weighty it is. Now, here's תרומה. terumah. תרומה terumah is not punishable
by כרת. karet? It's punishable by מיתה בידי שמים, mita b'yedei shamayim,
heavenly death. It sounds worse than כרת, karet. but actually in the
hierarchy it seems to be less bad. Okay, anyway, so what constitutes
שוגג by תרומה? terumah? Certainly an error in the facts. Certainly if
you didn't know it was prohibited. What about this other possibility of
not knowing how weighty it was? How would that play out here?
So let's take a look according to what אביי says. הכל מודים
בתרומה שאין חייב עליה חומש, hakol modim b'terumah she'ein chayav aleha chomesh,
you're not חייב חומש chayav chomesh עד שישגוג בלאו שבה. Until you
actually make a mistake about the prohibition. You think it's not prohibited.
So that's a חידוש. So the גמרא says הכל מודים. Who is
it that agrees? מאן מאן? man man? Who is that? רבי יוחנן.
It's רבי יוחנן. פשיטא? pshita. Obvious. Not so obvious to me. If
רבי יוחנן says not knowing כרת karet, is enough, maybe not knowing
מיתה בידי שמים mita b'yedei shamayim is enough. So the גמרא says,
but the גמרא thinks it's obvious, פשיטא. כי אמר רבי יוחנן היכא
דאיכא כרת. ki amar Rabbi Yochanan heicha d'ika karet. When does רבי
יוחנן say that not knowing כרת karet, suffices to call you שוגג?
When there is כרת. karet. היכא דליכא כרת לא. heicha d'leika karet
lo. If there's no כרת karet like here, there's not an error
in כרת, karet so of course that's not enough. So the גמרא
says no. מהו דתימא? I might have thought מיתה במקום כרת עומדת.
mita b'makom karet omedet. Right? מיתה בידי שמים mita b'yedei shamayim is
essentially takes the role of כרת in this scenario. וכי שגג במיתה
נמי ליהוי חייב. vechi shagag b'mita nami lehei chayav. When you err
regarding
מיתה, mita, that's also considered enough of an error because it's by
analogy to making a mistake of כרת. Here you made a mistake
about the punishment as well, the מיתה, Misa and maybe you're considered
שוגג. קמשמע לן kamashma lan that that doesn't count. For רבי יוחנן
it is specific to כרת and therefore here since there is no
כרת, the only way you're שוגג is if you don't know it's
prohibited. That's at least what אביי says. רבא disagrees. רבא אמר. Rava
amar. No, רבי יוחנן would say the same thing here. מיתה במקום
כרת עומדת, mita b'makom karet omedet, וחומש במקום קרבן קאי. v'chomesh b'makom
korban ka'i. It's like mutatis mutandis. Right? The מיתה בידי שמים mita
b'yedei shamayim takes the place of כרת, וחומש v'chomesh takes the place
of a קרבן. So the same way by a קרבן making an
error of כרת is enough of a mistake, by this making an
error of the מיתה בידי שמים mita b'yedei shamayim is also enough
of a mistake. And therefore in that case even though you know
it's prohibited, you'd be enough in error in order to bring the,
in order to bring the חומש. chomesh. Now I do want to
say something about the way I've been framing the idea of the
error of כרת. I've been framing the idea of the error of
כרת is that since you didn't know how weighty it was, you're
not seen as as willful. Okay, and that's also what makes you
שב מידיעתו. shav miyedi'ato. We might have said that had
you... could have been the גמרא'ס Gemara's question about the מיתה בידי
שמים. Misa BiYedei Shamayim. Not that מיתה בידי שמים Misa BiYedei Shamayim
wasn't weighty, but that maybe it doesn't play the same technical role
as כרת in the role it plays in terms of bringing a
קרבן. And that explains רבא'ס Rava's language. רבא doesn't say מיתה Misa
is very weighty and yes you are a שוגג. רבא says מיתה
Misa is equivalent to כרת. מיתה Misa. does for חומש Chomesh what
כרת does for קרבן. So it seems to be very specific that
the thing you made a mistake in is central to the punishment
that we're talking about, and the same way כרת is what קרבן
hinges on the כרת, here the חומש Chomesh hinges on the מיתה.
mitah Okay, so that's a different way of framing it, but either
way you have this debate and interestingly we rule like רבי יוחנן
that even if somebody knows they're violating, they just don't know that
it's punishable by כרת, they're seen enough in error and enough not
as willful that they actually are entitled to bring a קרבן, which
I think is a very nice thing, very forgiving approach.
Yes, רבי יוחנן came up a couple of times over here, רבי
יוחנן.
Oh yeah, he's a total אפסחיא. Afsachia. All right, so now the
גמרא comes on. Okay, now we switch from a lot of that,
which I'm sure was a little weighty, that whole discussion, to something
I think a lot more accessible, but ties into this idea of
not knowing when שבת Shabbos? is. So you know, the whole idea,
what do you mean not knowing when שבת Shabbos is? How'd you
lose sense of when שבת Shabbos. is? So you're on some desert
island and you got mistake which day it is. So the גמרא,
all right, so the גמרא talks about being on a desert island
and not knowing what day it is. What do you do? Right?
You don't want to violate שבת, Shabbos so what do you do?
So let's take a look. אמר הונא, Amar Huna, היה מהלך בדרך,
haya mehalech baderech, or just say היה מהלך במדבר, haya mehalech bamidbar,
anyway, because בדרך baderech still implies that you're near civilization. You're going
in the wilderness ואינו יודע אימתא שבת, ve'eino yodeia eimasa Shabbos, and
you don't know what day is שבת. Shabbos. You totally lost track
of the days. So what do you do? מונה ששה ימים ומשמר
יום אחד. moneh shisha yamim umeshamer yom echad.
You count six days and then you keep the seventh day, you
know, the day you're in you treat as if it were Sunday,
and then you count the seventh day and you treat that as
שבת. Shabbos Now what do you do? Means you're allowed to do
מלאכה those six days? Why are you allowed to do מלאכה those
six days? There's ספק שבת safek Shabbos and it's a ספק safek
biblical violation. So let's take a look where the גמרא goes with
this. חייא בר רב Chiyya Bar Rav אמר, משמר יום אחד ומונה
ששה. meshamer yom echad umoneh shisha. No, you start with a שבת.
Shabbos Not today, you're in the middle of the today when you
realized, so the next day, the full day you treat as שבת.
Shabbos This is the way רש"י Rashi explains it and then you
follow it with six full days, so you treat today as if
it's Friday, the day you all of a sudden realize you lost
track.
Even then, you know for sure like tomorrow couldn't be?
No, the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to deal with if you know how
you can eliminate certain days. Here you don't know you can eliminate
anything. Okay, so here's the debate though, which way do you start?
Six and one or one and six? So the גמרא says במאי
קמיפלגי? bemai kamiflagi? What do they debate? מר סבר כברייתו של עולם
mar savar kevriyaso shel olam ומר סבר כאדם הראשון. umar savar keAdam
HaRishon. One says like the original שבת Shabbos of creation, there were
six days and then there was שבת, Shabbos? so here you don't
know what is what, so you follow that pattern. The other
says no, you follow the pattern of אדם הראשון. Adam HaRishon. אדם
הראשון Adam HaRishon was created midday Friday, so you woke up in
the middle and you don't know what day it is, so you're
like אדם הראשון. Adam HaRishon. So today is Friday so tomorrow will
be שבת. Shabbos, Okay, so again what's that based on? I don't
know. It certainly seems to me that in terms of sort of
having the psychological religious experience of שבת, Shabbos. doing six and one
makes a lot more sense than one and six. Okay, but anyway,
that's the debate. So now the גמרא continues. Let's take a
look. גמרא says like this. מתיבי. Meisvei. I'll ask, we have a
ברייתא Baraisa that directly addresses this. היה מהלך בדרך, haya mehalech baderech,
you were going on the way ואינו יודע אימתא שבת, ve'eino yodeia
eimasa Shabbos, you don't know when שבת Shabbos. is. משמר יום אחד
לששה. meshamer yom echad leshisha. You observe one day for six that
you weren't observing. So since it says one day for six, it
sounds like the six have already passed. מאי לאו מונה ששה ומשמר
יום אחד? mai lav moneh shisha umeshamer yom echad? Doesn't this sound
like you count six days and the seventh is שבת, Shabbos like
the first opinion? גמרא says לא, you don't have to read it
that way. משמר יום אחד ומונה ששה. meshamer yom echad umoneh shisha.
You start with a שבת Shabbos, and then you count six. אי
הכי, I hachi, משמר יום אחד לששה? meshamer yom echad leshisha? It
shouldn't say you keep one day for the six. It should have
said משמר יום אחד ומונה ששה מיבעי ליה. meshamer yom echad umoneh
shisha mibaei lei. It should have said you keep one day and
then you count six. ועוד, Ve'od, and we have another ברייתא. Baraisa.
תניא, Tanya, we heard in the ברייתא. Baraisa. היה מהלך בדרך או
במדבר, haya mehalech baderech o bamidbar, you were going on the way
or the wilderness ואינו יודע אימתא שבת, ve'eino yodeia eimasa Shabbos, you
don't know when שבת Shabbos, is. מונה ששה, moneh shisha, it's explicit
you count six ומשמר יום אחד, umeshamer yom echad, and then you
observe שבת. Shabbos תיובתא דחייא בר רב תיובתא, Tiyuvta deChiyya Bar Rav
tiyuvta, so that's a complete contradiction which, let's face it, that's the
position that certainly makes more sense, at least from the religious experiential
point, you keep six and then the seventh day you treat as
שבת. Shabbos What does this mean, the seventh day is שבת Shabbos.
*Shabbos* and the first six are not? How maybe the first six,
one of those first six are, maybe you're violating שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos*,
how can you go ahead? So that's what the גמרא *Gemara*'s going
to say. אמר רבא *Amar Rava* בכל יום ויום עושה לו כדי
פרנסתו *bechol yom v'yom oseh lo k'dei parnasato*. Every day you do
the minimum amount you need to survive. בר מההיא יומא *Bar mehahi
yoma*, except that one day, that day of שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* because
what's going to set set aside that seventh day? So that day
you don't do anything. So the גמרא *Gemara* says וההוא יומא לימות
*v'hahu yoma leimus*? So you're going to die that day? What if
you can't do enough to survive? המבתי *Hamavtei*? So what do you
want to do? So the גמרא *Gemara* says אוקי דעביד מעלי שבתא
טפי פרנסתו *okey d'avid me'alei shabbata tefei parnasato*. So fine, the day
before you do twice as much, enough to last you for the
following day. So the גמרא *Gemara* says like the מן *man*. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says ודילמא מעלי שבתא שבתא הוא *udilma me'alei shabbata
shabbata hu*? But so what? Maybe yesterday, right, it's very nice that
you want to do something to remember the concept of שבת Shabbat
*Shabbos*. But there's still an objective reality what day is שבת Shabbat.
*Shabbos*. And there's no way that tomorrow that I'm going to keep
as שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* has more halachic weight than today. Today is
also a ספק *safek* that maybe it's שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos*. So what
allows me today to do two days' worth of work, right? It's
not פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh, *pikuach nefesh* right now. פיקוח נפש pikuach
nefesh *Pikuach nefesh* is only one unit of work. Tomorrow there'll be
a פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh *pikuach nefesh* and I'll do work tomorrow
but today all I have to do is one day's worth of
work. אלא *Ela*, so the גמרא *Gemara* says you're right, you can't
do two days of work today. Today might be שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos*.
אלא כל יום ויום עושה לו פרנסתו *Ela kol yom v'yom oseh
lo parnasato*, every day you do the minimum amount of work you
need to do to survive. אפילו ההוא יומא *Afilu hahu yoma*, even
the day you're keeping as שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos*. So what's special about
the day I'm keeping as שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos*? וההוא יומא במה מינכר
minkar ליה *V'hahu yoma b'mai minchar lei*? What makes that day distinct?
בקידושא ואבדלתא *Bekidusha v'avdalta*, you make קידוש *Kiddush* and הבדלה *Havdalah*. I
assume it doesn't mean with wine and בשמים *besamim*, I mean I
don't know unless you happen to have that on you. But anyway,
it means just even verbally saying קידוש *Kiddush* and הבדלה *Havdalah*, you
verbally set it aside and distinguish it, which is a very nice
idea, you know that again it sort of parallels what we discussed
before. How can you think that מלאכה *melacha* is permissible and still
know the day is שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*? There for the sake of
a קרבן *korban*, the גמרא *Gemara* needed you to know in some
way in terms of the prohibition of מלאכה *melacha*. Here, since anyway
you're always doing the bare minimum, what gives it the extra distinctiveness
is the קידוש *Kiddush* and הבדלה *Havdalah*. One minute.
Why? We eliminate a ברייתא *braita*? What? We eliminate a ברייתא *braita*?
What do you mean? No, you have שומר *shomer* anything. You are
משמר *mishamer*, you're משמר *mishamer* it by קידוש *Kiddush* and הבדלה *Havdalah*.
So the גמרא *Gemara* just it was very vague in those ברייתות
*braitos*. אמר רבא *Amar Rava* אם היה מכיר *Im haya makir*, now
the גמרא *Gemara* gets to Michael's point about let's say you can
eliminate some days. אם היה מכיר מקצת היום שיצא בו *Im haya
makir miktzat hayom sheyatza bo*, עושה מלאכה כל היום כולו *oseh melacha
kol hayom kulo*. If you know like, you know, oh, you know
that you left on like a, you know, you know you left
on a Wednesday, right? And you know that it's been, so wait,
what's the scenario? Let me just... What?
It's much more plausible. You know off by a day, you don't
know exactly what day of the week it is, but you know
it wasn't on a Wednesday but it might be Friday, it might
be Sunday. Right. Oh, right.
So here's the way רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says it, right, so you
could just know that you're off by a day, but רש"י *Rashi*
says the following way. You know that today is
three days since you left. You forgot what day of the week
you left. But you know you've been traveling for three days. So
you can figure, okay, but if I know I've been traveling for
three days, I know that three days ago wasn't שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos*.
So at least I can eliminate one day of the week. Because
since I know how many days I've been traveling, even though I
forget which day of the week it is, I know that I
didn't leave on a שבת *Shabbos*. So that day of the week
I can eliminate and that day I should do as much מלאכה
*melacha* as possible to store up for the rest of the week.
Okay. עושה מלאכה כל היום כולו *Oseh melacha kol hayom kulo*. You
do מלאכה *melacha* that entire day. Not just you're allowed to, you
probably should in order that you can store up for the rest
of the week. So the גמרא *Gemara* says פשיטא *peshita*, that's obvious.
No, מהו דתימא *mahu d'teima*, I might have thought כיון דשבת לא
נפיק *keivan d'Shabbos lo nafik*, you know you didn't leave on a
שבת *Shabbos*, so you get one day. But maybe you could also
say במעלי שבתא נמי לא נפיק *b'ma'alei shabbata nami lo nafik*. I
probably didn't leave on a Friday. Who goes traveling on a trip
on a Friday, to ערב שבת *erev Shabbos*? So maybe I actually
can figure out two days I'm safe. The גמרא *Gemara* says no,
that assumption you can't make. והא איכא נמי בחמישי בשבתא דנפיק ליה
למיעבד מלאכה תרי יומי *V'ha icha nami b'chamishi b'shabbata d'nafik lei l'mi'avad
melacha terei yomei*. So even if I went out on a Thursday,
at least I know two days that I'm safe. I know I
didn't go out, the day I left wasn't שבת *Shabbos* and maybe
I also know the day I left wasn't a Friday. So I've
got two days that I know I'm good for. So the גמרא
*Gemara* says קמשמע לן *kamashma lan*, no, this teaches you זמנין דמשכח
שיירתא ומקרי ונפיק *zimnin d'meshkach shayarta umakrei v'nafik*. Sometimes there's a caravan
going and this is your one chance to hop on with a
caravan and sometimes you will leave on a Friday. But you'll never
leave on a שבת *Shabbos*. So if you know that, you could
know that at least, you know, every week from the day that
you left is a non-שבת *Shabbos* day and you're okay. Now I
want to say something about about this about the minimum that you
do. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* asks an important question. If you take a
look at תוספות Tosafot. *Tosafos*, עושה כדי פרנסתו *oseh k'dei parnasato*, תוספות
*Tosafos* says like this: אבל להלך יכול כל מה שירצה *Aval l'haleich
yachol kol mah sheyirtzeh*. He says, how about walking? You can walk
as much as you want each day, we don't have to worry
about תחומין *tchumin* or whatnot. Why? Because he says רק ביום שמשמר
*rak bayom shemeshameir*, maybe not the day that you're keeping as שבת
*Shabbos*. דאלת"ה *D'ilav hachi*, if you're not walking, לא יגיע לעולם לישוב
*lo yagia l'olam l'yishuv*, you're never going to get back to civilization.
So he says, so you know, so that you're allowed to do,
maybe that's only... and so on. And והא דקאמר במאי מינכר, why
don't you say so, it's מינכר that you're not, you're not traveling
on that day? משום דאין היכר שבת במאי שיושב ואינו הולך. mishum
de'ein heker Shabbos bemai sheyoshev ve'eino holeich. It's not so obvious. And
אינמי, inami, אפילו ביום שמשמר הולך כמו שרוצה. afilu beyom shemeshameir holeich
kemo sherotze.
Even on the day you're observing שבת, you can keep on traveling
because you're trying to get back to civilization. Okay, now that raises
an interesting question which is, you know, the גמרא sort of imagines
that somehow I can do work today and provide like enough, you
know, enough food for today, right? But that often that's not the
scenario. Like often maybe, you know, I have to today I'm not
going, you know, today it's like long-term. Let me give you an
example. Let's say תוספות talks about walking, but let's say it's about
carrying. Let's say you've got, you know, your canteen and your food
and whatnot, right? So can I carry on שבת? So I'm trying
to get back to civilization, but my carrying today isn't helping me
stay alive today, right? Today I stay alive just by drinking. And
it's really helping me get to civilization which will maybe help me
stay alive long-term, right? But actually I could just walk, I don't
have to carry, but the reason I'm carrying is so that I'll
have the food on me tomorrow and I need the food tomorrow.
So it's presumably that all that is permissible because all that is
in the category of פיקוח נפש, pikuach nefesh right? If I don't
do these types of activities, eventually I'm going to run out of
food and I'm going to die without having reached civilization. But it
raises this, you know, it creates this interesting scenario where I'm doing
מלאכה today which might be שבת in order to save for פיקוח
נפש pikuach nefesh. that's going to be in the future. Now, if
you translate that, it's pretty obvious. Let's say, for example, somebody is
dying and they need a doctor on Sunday, and the only doctor
that can, and I'm the only doctor who can help this person,
and in order to get to that person I have to drive
or fly out on a plane or whatever on שבת. Right? So
it doesn't matter that I'm doing it for a פיקוח נפש pikuach
nefesh tomorrow rather than a פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh. today, you're still
doing it for פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh. But the גמרא sort of
simplifies it, like all I have to worry about is just providing
for myself today, you know, and do the minimum today. There's a
lot of scenarios where you have to do a lot today in
order to prevent yourself, you know, to stave off the possibility of
פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh. in the future and so on, which is
somewhat alluded to in this תוספות. Yes.
An example of losing track, the first ship that circumnavigated the world,
by the time they made it around, they were off by a
day because
the International Date Line, and they didn't know that. Sort of like
Jules Verne's 80 Days Around the World. Yeah, but all those stories
about being washed up on a desert island, right? You know, so
that's a question too. It's got to be pretty difficult to live
your life like this, that always the only thing that's allowed is
the minimum, which is only within the חשבון cheshbon of פיקוח נפש.
pikuach nefesh Oh, anyway, so let's now just do, get to the
bottom of the, yes.
Same thing with people who were incarcerated. Oh, for
real?
They what, what do you mean and you don't know what day
of the week it is?
If you're in prison and like, you know, let's say you were
in solitary. You can lose track of time.
You can ask the guards, can't you?
They might lie. They might lie.
Ah, what if you're in a foreign country prison where they don't,
right, right. Okay, so yeah, so definitely it is relevant. All right,
so now the גמרא says, let's now back to these questions about
how many קרבנות you bring. היודע עיקר שבת, hayodeia ikar Shabbos, if
you know שבת exists but you forget which day, you bring for
every שבת. And but, and if you didn't know that שבת existed
or you forgot שבת existed altogether, you bring one קרבן. מנא הני
מילי, mena hanei milei, where do you get this difference from about
forgetting the existence of שבת is one קרבן, forgetting which day is
שבת is a קרבן for each שבת? אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה
בר אבוה, Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha, תרי קראי כתיבי,
trei krayei ketivei,
there's two פסוקים. pesukim. ושמרו בני ישראל את השבת, veshamru venei Yisrael
et haShabbos, בני ישראל benei Yisrael should observe השבת, haShabbos,
singular. וכתיב, ukhtiv, את שבתותי, et Shabbetotai, my שבתות, Shabbatos, plural, תשמורו,
tishmoru, you should observe. הכיצד, hakeitzad, how do you, one refers to
a single שבת, one to multiple? How do you deal with this?
ושמרו בני ישראל את השבת, veshamru venei Yisrael et haShabbos, that's not
a problem, it gives us an opportunity to make a דרשה. drasha.
ושמרו בני ישראל את השבת, veshamru venei Yisrael et haShabbos, שמירה אחת
לשבתות הרבה. shemira achat leShabbatot harbe. So that means that there's one
observance, we're treating it all as one big שבת. Many שבתות, Shabbatos,
but they're treated as one. Okay, so you could have a type
of a forgetting that is about a one basic mistake for many
שבתות. Shabbatos. You forgot about the idea of שבת. Okay? ואת שבתותי
תשמורו, ve'et Shabbetotai tishmoru, my multiple שבתות Shabbatos you should observe. שמירה
אחת לכל שבת ושבת. shemira achat lechol Shabbos vaShabbos. Each שבת is
treated separately. So are all the שבתות Shabbatos treated as one, or
is each one treated separately? So sometimes one way, sometimes the other
way. What's the difference? As רש"י says, לא מסר כתוב אלא לחכמים,
lo masar katuv ela lachachamim, the, you know, the sages are empowered
to interpret it, and they'll say, it's all treated as one when
you make a mistake, you forgot about שבת, the existence of שבת,
and they're treated as multiple when you forgot which day was שבת
and you forgot, and then every separate שבת you forgot that was
a שבת. So מתיב ליה רב נחמן, mativ lei Rav Nachman, so
רב נחמן Rav Nachman says. You know, I get the point of
the דרשה, drasha, I just think that the פסוקים psukim should be
flipped. רבי יצחק אדרבא איפכא מסתברא. Rabbi Yitzhak adarabba ipkha mistabra. I'll
say the same דרשה drasha but I think you should flip the
פסוקים. psukim. ושמרו בני ישראל את השבת, ve-shamru venei yisrael et ha-shabbat,
there it says you should observe the Shabbat, שמירה אחת לכל שבת,
shmirah ahat le-khol shabbat, one observance for one שבת. So that means
every שבת is a separate thing, and therefore every שבת is a
separate
קרבן. ושבתותי תשמורו, ve-shabbotai tishmoru, my multiple Shabbats you should
observe. So therefore, שמירה אחת לשבתות הרבה, shmirah ahat le-shabbotot harbeh, so
one observing for many Shabbats. So therefore even for many Shabbats it's
only one קרבן, that's when you forgot the existence of שבת. So
we're basically saying the same thing, just whether you emphasize, you know,
which way you read the פסוקים. psukim. But basically, we have a
hint in the פסוקים psukim and then חז"ל hazal come and tell
us that if you make a mistake about שבת in principle, it's
one קרבן. If you make a mistake every week about what day
is שבת, then it's a קרבן for each שבת. And now tomorrow
we will turn to forgetting about the מלאכות.
So in the desert they're bringing a קרבן after they get back
and he knows?
No, why would you bring a קרבן? What you did was פיקוח
נפש. pikuach nefesh.
Yeah, but you could have said you're שוגג because you didn't know
which day was שבת.
Doesn't matter. What you did was פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh, I don't
understand.
I mean like you're negligent by not knowing which day was שבת.
I mean you could have kept better track. You'd say that?
No. I mean if you're שוגג because basically what you're saying is
you're שוגג to lead to a פיקוח נפש situation. So no, you
still what you did though was still פיקוח נפש. You know? So
even though you were a little bit to blame for having been
in that situation, right, so you're still... Right. If we're going camping
and I'm negligent and all of our equipment falls over the cliff
and now it's שבת and we have to violate שבת, I'm... you
know, still what we're doing is we're doing a פיקוח נפש, you
know?
This discussion has a bearing on places like the Arctic Circle where
there's no solar...
Oh, you know, it could, but there more the פוסקים poskim want
to say let's come up with, figure out a פסק psak to
deal with it rather than leaving it. Right. Every 56 minutes שחרית
מנחה מעריב. shacharit mincha maariv. Yeah, some of those cases.
I have a תענית גדולה. ta'anit gdola. I was wiped out all
yesterday. Couldn't do anything. I was...
הרב אבא HaRav Abba was a little disturbed because I cut her
hair.
From top to bottom, I was... Joe took me racquetball playing on
Sunday. It's gory, I'm a mess. Next time we go Saturday night
so at least I have a weekend day to recover.
I think there's a message in there.
You think you're saying that
I need to stop exercising? No, go more, I know. So in
the moves cases, do you know if it's enough for him if
you were שוגג on מיתה mitah. versus כרת? מיתה בידי שמים mitah
b'yedei shamayim versus כרת. Is that a... would you be considered a
שוגג?
I think that it looks like he's very much focusing on the
technical point of the פסוק. pasuk. If the פסוק pasuk talks about
קרבן, if the פסוק pasuk talks about כרת, so that's where the
שוגג has to exist. On the things that are addressed in the
פסוק. pasuk. The לאו, the כרת, the קרבן. You mean if you
confuse...
So in your case, if you... No, so... So your question is,
okay, I made a mistake about כרת. I thought it was מיתה.
I wasn't... you know, that's your question about רבי יוחנן as well.
Right. I think it's a good point. I think if you say
it's the technical point like I said, that the כרת is a
constituent of the קרבן, then maybe the answer would be yes. Although,
yes that that would be enough to bring a קרבן because it's...
of course you would have to say you're still שב מידיעה, shav
mi-yedi'ah, I known it's כרת and I wouldn't have done it. Okay.
If you say it's about the weightiness of it, then I would...
then I think it's a bigger question. He should have... you know,
he still was aware that it was pretty weighty. But the גמרא
indicates it's a little bit more about the technical point, the constituent
part of the...
how you get this to work.
Yeah, I think so. At least... yeah. At least. So, I'm going
back to this Hanukkah
thing.
Is it point to say that, you know, nice, but to manufacture
a miracle and then say that we're going to make a ברכה
bracha on it? You know, that's a whole other...
But now I don't understand, the ברכה bracha you have to say
the ברכה bracha is about the... the idea that it would light
for seven days for eight days is already in the Book of
Maccabees. It's clearly already within the H.C.P.
which shows it wasn't a miracle.
But there's still eight days of dedication and which were commemorated by
the
lighting of the מנורה menorah and central part of the dedication in
the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. And שעשה נסים לאבותינו she-asah nissim la-avoteinu
is a very generic ברכה. bracha. So there's nothing that asks to
make it about that, about נס, nes, about that specifically. Hi! Hi!
It was great yesterday. Wasn't it? You did it so nicely. It
was so interesting. My kids first
of
all had a blast.
Your son, Lachie's more over the top.
And I thought it appealed to a lot of different types. Yeah.
I was disappointed that there weren't more guys there, but when I...
I thought it was pretty well attended.
When I approached them this morning, they're like, "But we switched the
date." I know.
People have things to do.
Okay, now, everyone, I'll do my best
for this. Good... this...
So awesome to see Louisa too. Oh yeah. That was
my...
that was the highlight.
She looked very happy.
She looks so happy. He seems like a good guy, worthy of
her.